Anna Alice Cutler Papers, 1881-1957
Smith College Archives
Anna Alice Cutler Papers
1881-1957
Cutler, Anna Alice, 1864-1957
RG 42 UUID:42934500-6ff0-4bbd-9ce3-34104bf65146
2 boxes (10 linear inches)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Professor of Philosophy. Contains biographical material, correspondence, critiques, photographs and publications.
Instructor of Logic, 1893-95
Instructor, English Department, 1897 -99
Instructor of Philosophy, 1899-1902
Associate Professor of Philosophy, 1902- 05
Professor of Philosophy, 1905- 30
Philosophy Department Chair, 1924-1930
Anna Alice Cutler was born on January 24, 1864 in New Haven, Connecticut to Evarts and Ellen L. Knight Cutler. She was a member of the Smith College class of 1885 and, upon graduating from the college, taught classics at a private school in New Haven while working on her MA from Yale. During 1892-93, Cutler headed the Philosophy department at Rockford College. In 1893, Cutler was appointed instructor of Logic at Smith College, however she left to continue her graduate study, and received a Ph.D. from Yale in 1896. In 1897, Cutler returned to the Smith faculty to teach in the English department, then the Philosophy department, where she became an instructor, associate professor, full professor, and in 1924, chair of the department.
Cutler lived in Tyler House for the first 33 years of its existence, from 1897 until her retirement in 1930. She was the first director of Juniper Lodge, and established an endowment for it. In 1952, Cutler was awarded an honorary degree of Doctor of Humane Letters from the college. She used 1929-1930 as a sabbatical year, before retiring after 25 years as a professor at the college in 1930. On retiring, she spent several months in Europe, before returning to New Haven, serving on the board of the Visiting Nurse Association, as well as on committees of the American Association of University Women. She spent 2 years as president of the Smith College Club of New Haven, and was a member of various church committees. Cutler died in the summer of 1957.
The Anna Alice Cutler Papers are separated in to four series as follows:
Series I: Biographical Materials
This section consists of Cutler's birth certificate (copy), information from her studies at Yale University, information of the degrees obtained, promotions received and her retirement.
Series II: Correspondence
This section consists of five folders housing correspondence to and from other faculty members and one regarding the death of Harry Norman Gardner. The folders are filed alphabetically.
Series III: Publications
This sections contains a critique and four of Cutler's publications. The titles are:
Aesthetical Factors in Kant's Theory of Knowledge, 1898
Gist from Quackery, n. d.
The Pendulum, n. d.
Sense About Schools, n. d.
Series IV: Photographs
This part of the collection consists of one folder in box # 740 with photos dated from 1881 through 1915 and a large photo album in box # 739 dated 1885.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
History of the Collection
The Anna Alice Cutler Papers were donated over a period of time to the Smith College Archives from a variety of sources.
Additional Information
Related Material
80. Class of 1885 Records
- Photo Album 1885 (Box 739)
- Biographical Materials 1864-1957 (Box 740, Folder 1)
- Notes and Trip Information 1916-1929 (Box 740, Folder 2)
- Correspondence: Margaret Storrs 1945-1957 (Box 740, Folder 3)
- Correspondence: Frances Luther Rich 1948 (Box 740, Folder 4)
- Correspondence: Hilda (Edwards) Hamlin 1956-57 (Box 740, Folder 5)
- Correspondence: William Allan Neilson 1929-1938 (Box 740, Folder 6)
- Correspondence: Eleanor E. Cutler 1909 (Box 740, Folder 7)
- Correspondence: Regarding the death of Harry Norman Gardner 1927 (Box 740, Folder 8)
- Critiques of Bestor I. Burnett 1954, n. d. (Box 740, Folder 9)
- Degrees: A. M. 1889 (Box 740, Folder 10)
- Degrees: Ph.D. 1896 (Box 740, Folder 11)
- Degrees: Honorary 1952 (Box 740, Folder 12)
- Juniper Lodge 1924-25 (Box 740, Folder 13)
- Photographs 1881-1915 (Box 740, Folder 14)
- Publication: Aesthetical Factors in Kant's Theory of Knowledge 1898 (Box 740, Folder 15)
- Publication: Gist from Quackery n. d. (Box 740, Folder 16)
- Publication: The Pendulum n. d. (Box 740, Folder 17)
- Publication: Sense About Schools n. d. (Box 740, Folder 18)
- Promotions 1905, 1924 (Box 740, Folder 19)
- Retirement 1929 (Box 740, Folder 20)
- Yale University 1901, n. d. (Box 740, Folder 21)